Has anyone among you ever been exposed to tear gas?
هل من بينكم من تعرض في حياته للغاز المسيل للدموع؟
Tear gas? Anyone?
الغاز المسيل للدموع؟ هل من أحد؟
I'm sorry to hear that, so you might know that it's a very toxic substance,
آسف لسماع ذلك، إذًا ربما تعرفون أنه مادة سامة جدًا،
but you might not know that it's a very simple molecule
لكن ربما لا تعرفون أنه جزيء بسيط جدًا
with an unpronouncable name:
له أسم صعب النطق:
it's called chlorobenzalmalononitrile.
فهو يدعى كلورو بنزال مالونوتريل.
I made it.
قلتها.
It's decades old, but it's becoming very trendy among police forces
يبلغ عمره عقود، لكنه أصبح شائعًا وسط قوات الشرطة
around the planet lately, it seems,
حول الكوكب في الآونة الأخيرة، على ما يبدو،
and according to my experience as a non-voluntary breather of it,
ووفقًا لتجربتي الخاصة كمتنفس له غصباً،
tear gas has two main but quite opposite effects.
للغاز المسيل للدموع تأثيران رئيسيان لكن متضادان تمامًا.
One, it can really burn your eyes,
الأول، يمكنه حرق عينيك حقًا،
and two, it can also help you to open them.
والثاني، يمكنه أيضًا مساعدتك لتفتحهم.
Tear gas definitely helped to open mine to something
ساعد الغاز المسيل للدموع بالتأكيد على فتح عيني على شيء ما
that I want to share with you this afternoon:
أريد أن أشاركه معكم في هذا اليوم:
that livestreaming the power of independent broadcasts through the web
أنّ البث الحي، قوة البث المستقلة عبر الشبكة
can be a game-changer in journalism,
يمكن أن تكون مغيرة لقواعد لعبة الصحافة،
in activism, and as I see it, in the political discourse as well.
في النشاط السياسي، وكما أرى، في الخطاب السياسي أيضًا.
That idea started to dawn on me in early 2011
بدأت تلك الفكرة في الظهور لي أواخر 2011
when I was covering a protest in São Paulo.
حين كنت أقوم بتغطية احتجاجات في ساو باولو.
It was the marijuana march,
قد كانت مسيرة من أجل المريجوانا،
a gathering of people asking for the legalization of cannabis.
جمع من الناس يطالبون بإجازة قانونية للحشيش.
When that group started to move,
حين بدأت تلك المجموعة في التحرك،
the riot police came from the back with rubber bullets, bombs,
هاجمتها قوات مكافحة الشغب من الخلف بالرصاص المطاطي، والقنابل،
and then the gas.
ثم الغاز.
But to make a long story short,
لكن لاختصار هذه القصة الطويلة،
I had entered that protest as the editor-in-chief
كنت قد دخلت تلك المظاهرة كرئيس تحرير
of a well-established printed magazine where I'd worked for 11 years,
لمجلة مطبوعة راسخة عملت بها 11 عامًا،
and thanks to this unsolicited effects of tear gas,
وبفضل تأثير الغاز المسيل للدموع غير المتوقع،
I left it as a journalist that was now committed to new ways
خرجت كصحفي متعهد الآن لطرق جديدة
of sharing the raw experience of what it's like to be there, actually.
لمشاركة التجربة الخام كما لو كنت هناك، حقًا.
So in the following week, I was back in the streets,
لذا في الأسابيع التالية، عدت إلى الشوارع،
but that time, I wasn't a member of any media outlet anymore.
لكن تلك المرة، لم أعد ممثل لأى منفذ إعلامي.
I was there as an independent livestreamer, and all I had with me
كنت هناك كمراسل مباشر مستقل، وكل ما كان معي
was basically borrowed equipment.
معدات أساسية مقترضة.
I had a very simple camera and a backpack with 3G modems.
كان لدي كاميرا بسيطة جدًا وحقيبة ظهر بها مودم يدعم تقنية الجيل الثالث
And I had this weblink that could be shared through social media,
ولدي هذا الرابط الذي من خلاله يمكنني المشاركة عبر وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي،
could be put in any website,
ويمكنني وضعه في أي موقع على الإنترنت،
and that time, the protest went along fine.
وتلك المرة، المظاهرة امتدت على نحو جيد.
There was no violence.
لم يكن هناك عنف.
There was no action scenes.
لم يكن هناك مشاهد إثارة.
But there was something really exciting,
لكن كان هناك شيئًا مثير حقًا،
because I could see at a distance the TV channels covering it,
كان يمكنني مشاهدة قنوات التليفزيون التي تغطي على بعد،
and they had these big vans and the teams and the cameras,
وهم يملكون تلك العربات الضخمة والفرق والكاميرات،
and I was basically doing the same thing
وقد كنت بصورة أساسية أقوم بالشيء ذاته
and all I had was a backpack.
وكل ما أملكه كان حقيبة ظهر.
And that was really exciting to a journalist,
وكان هذا فعلًا مثير لصحفي،
but the most interesting part was when I got back home, actually,
لكن الجزء الأكثر إثارة حين عدت إلى المنزل، في الحقيقة،
because I learned that I had been watched
لأني علمت أني قد شُوهدت
by more than 90,000 people,
بأكثر من 90,000 شخص،
and I got hundreds of emails and messages of people asking me, basically,
ووصلني المئات من الرسائل من أناس تسألني، في الأساس،
how did I do it,
كيف فعلت ذلك،
how it was possible to do such a thing.
كيف من الممكن فعل مثل ذلك الشيء.
And I learned something else, that that was actually the first time
وعلمت شيء آخر، أن تلك هي المرة الأولى على الإطلاق فعليًا
that somebody had ever done a livestreaming in a street protest
التي يقوم فيها شخص ببث مباشر لاحتجاجات في شارع
in the country.
في البلد.
And that really shocked me,
وقد صدمني ذلك،
because I was no geek, I was no technology guy,
لأني لم أكن شخص مهوس بالتكنولوجيا،
and all the equipment needed was already there,
وكل المعدات المطلوبة كانت هناك بالفعل،
was easily available.
كانت متاحة بسهولة.
And I realized that we had a frontier here,
وأدركت أننا نمتلك الريادة هنا،
a very important one,
أهم شيء على الإطلاق،
that it was just a matter of changing the perspective,
والذي هو مجرد مسألة تغيير وجهة النظر،
and the web could be actually used,
ويمكن استخدام شبكة الإنترنت حقيقةً،
already used, as a colossal and uncontrollable
وبالفعل تستخدم، كأكبر قناة أو شبكة تلفزيونية لا يمكن مراقبتها
and highly anarchical TV channel, TV network,
والأوسع انتشارًا على الإطلاق،
and anyone with very basic skills and very basic equipment,
وأي شخص لديه مهارات ومعدات أولية جدًا،
even someone like me who had this little stuttering issue,
شخص مثلي حتى لديه هذه القضية الضئيلة المتعثرة،
so if it happens, bear with me please,
حتى لو حدث ذلك، تحملوني من فضلكم،
even someone like me could become a broadcaster.
شخص مثلي حتى قد يصبح مذيع.
And that sounded revolutionary in my mind.
وذلك يبدو في عقلي ثوريًا.
So for the next couple of years,
لذا لعامين تاليين،
I started to experiment with livestreaming in different ways,
بدأت تجربة البث المباشر بطرق مختلفة،
not only in the streets but mostly in studios and in homes,
ليس في الشوارع فقط لكن غالبًا في الاستوديوهات والمنازل،
until the beginning of 2013, last year,
حتى بداية 2013، العام الماضي،
when I became the cofounder of a group called Mídia NINJA.
حين أصبحت المؤسس لمجموعة تدعى ميديا نينجا.
NINJA is an acronym
نينجا هي الحروف الأولى
that stands for Narrativas Independentes Jornalismo e Ação,
من العنوان: روايات مستـــقلة الصحافة والعمل،
It was a media group that had little media plan.
كانت مجموعة إعلامية لديها خطة إعلامية ضئيلة.
We didn't have any financial structure.
لم يكن لدينا أي هيكل مالي.
We were not planning to make money out of this,
لم نكن نخطط لجني المال من هذا،
which was wise, because you shouldn't try to make money out of journalism now.
والذي كان من الحكمة، لأنه لا يجب أن تحاول جني المال من الصحافة الآن.
But we had a very solid and clear conviction,
لكن كان لدينا قناعة صلبة وواضحة،
that we knew that the hyperconnected environment of social media
التي هي أننا عرفنا أن البيئة شديدة الاتصال بوسائل التواصل الاجتماعي
could maybe allow us to consolidate
قد تتيح لنا ربط
a network of experimental journalists throughout the country.
شبكة من الصحفيين التجريبيين عبر البلد.
So we launched a Facebook page first, and then a manifesto,
لذا أطلقنا أولًا صفحة فيس بوك، ثم بعد ذلك وثيقة أساسية،
and started to cover the streets in a very simple way.
وبدأنا بتغطية الشوارع بطريقة بسيطة جدًا.
But then something happened, something that wasn't predicted,
لكن بعد ذلك حدث شيء ما، شيء لم يكن منتظر،
that no one could have anticipated.
ولا يمكن لأحد توقعه.
Street protests started to erupt in São Paulo.
احتجاجات الشارع بدأت تنطلق في ساو باولو.
They began as very local and specific.
بدأوا محدودين ومحددين.
They were against the bus fare hike that had just happened in the city.
كانوا ضد ارتفاع تعريفة الأتوبيس التي قد تم تطبيقها في المدينة منذ فترة وجيزة.
This is a bus.
هذا أتوبيس.
It's written there, "Theft."
مكتوب عليه، "سرقة."
But those kind of manifestations started to grow,
لكن تلك الأنواع من التظاهرات أخذت في النمو،
and they kept happening.
واستمرت في الحدوث.
So the police violence against them started to grow as well.
لذا وبالتالي بدأ عنف الشرطة ضدهم في التصاعد.
But there was another conflict,
لكن كان هناك صراع آخر،
the one I believe that's more important here
الشيء الوحيد الذي أعتقد أنه أكثر أهمية هنا
to make my point that it was a narrative conflict.
لجعل وجهة نظري واضحة أنه كان صراع روايات.
There was this mainstream media version of the facts
كانت هناك وسائل الإعلام الرئيسية نسخة الحقائق
that anyone who was on the streets could easily challenge
التي أي شخص من الذين في الشوارع يمكن أن يتحداهم بسهولة
if they presented their own vision of what was actually happening there.
إذا قدموا رؤيتهم الخاصة لما كان يحدث هناك فعليًا.
And it was this clash of visions, this clash of narratives,
وكان هذا الصدام في الرؤى، هذا الصدام في الروايات،
that I think turned those protests
الذي أعتقد أنه حول تلك الاحتجاجات
into a long period in the country of political reckoning
لفترة طويلة من تصفية الحسابات السياسية في البلد
where hundreds of thousands of people,
حيث مئات الآلاف من الناس،
probably more than a million people
تقريبًا أكثر من مليون شخص
took to the streets in the whole country.
خرجوا للشوارع في كل أنحاء البلد.
But it wasn't about the bus fare hike anymore.
لكن لم يعد من أجل رفع تعريفة الأتوبيس.
It was about everything.
كان من أجل كل شيء.
The people's demands, their expectations,
مطالب الناس، توقعاتهم،
the reasons why they were on the streets
أسباب وجودهم في الشوارع
could be as diverse as they could be contradictory in many cases.
قد تكون متنوعة بقدر التناقض بينهم في العديد من القضايا.
If you could read it, you would understand me.
لو أمكنكم قراءته، لكنتم فهمتموني.
But it was in this environment of political catharsis
لكنها كانت بيئة للتنفيس السياسي
that the country was going through
الذي مرت خلاله البلد
that it had to do with politics, indeed,
ذلك ما كان ينبغي فعله في السياسة، فعلًا،
but it had to do also with a new way of organizing,
لكن ذلك كان ينبغي فعله أيضًا في طريقة جديدة للتنظيم،
through a new way of communicating.
عبر طريقة جديدة للاتصال.
It was in that environment that Mídia NINJA emerged
في هذه البيئة ظهرت ميديا نينجا
from almost anonymity to become a national phenomenon,
من عدم الكشف عن هويتها تقريبًا لتصبح ظاهرة قومية،
because we did have the right equipment.
لأننا قمنا بالتجهيز الصحيح.
We are not using big cameras.
إننا لم نستخدم الكاميرات الكبيرة.
We are using basically this.
نحن نستخدم هذه في الأساس.
We are using smartphones.
نستخدم الهواتف الذكية.
And that, actually, allowed us to become invisible in the middle of the protests,
وذلك، في الحقيقة، يسمح لنا أن نكون غير مرئيين في وسط الاحتجاجات،
but it allowed us to do something else:
لكن يسمح لنا بفعل شيء آخر:
to show what it was like to be in the protests,
نعرض كيف يكون الحال إذا كنت ضمن الاحتجاجات،
to present to people at home a subjective perspective.
لنقدم للناس في المنازل منظور ذاتي.
But there was something that is more important,
لكن كان هناك شيء أكثر أهمية،
I think, than the equipment.
أعتقد، أكثر من التجهيز.
It was our mindset,
أنه عقليتنا،
because we are not behaving as a media outlet.
لأننا لا نتصرف كمنفذ إعلامي.
We are not competing for news.
نحن لا نتنافس على الأخبار.
We are trying to encourage people,
نحن نحاول حث الناس، ودعوة الناس،
how to do this, how they also could become broadcasters.
كيف يفعلون هذا، كيف يمكنهم أيضًا أن يصبحوا مراسلين.
And that was crucial to turn Mídia NINJA from a small group of people,
وكان ذلك حاسم لتحويل ميديا نينجا من مجموعة صغيرة من الناس،
and in a matter of weeks,
وفي غضون أسابيع،
we multiplied and we grew exponentially throughout the country.
تضاعفنا وازددنا أضعافًا مضاعفةً عبر البلد.
So in a matter of a week or two, as the protests kept happening,
في غضون أسبوع أو اثنين، أستمرت الاحتجاجات،
we were hundreds of young people
كنا مئات من الشباب
connected in this network throughout the country.
متصلون بهذه الشبكة عبر البلد.
We were covering more than 50 cities at the same time.
كنا نقوم بتغطية أكثر من 50 مدينة في نفس الوقت.
That's something that no TV channel could ever do.
الشيء الذي لا يمكن لقناة تليفزيونية فعله أبدًا.
That was responsible for turning us suddenly, actually,
كان ذلك منطقي لتحويلنا فجأةً، حقيقةً،
into kind of the mainstream media of social media.
لنوع من إعلام التيار الرئيسي في مواقع التواصل الاجتماعي.
So we had a couple of thousands of followers on our Facebook page,
لذا أصبح لدينا ألفين من المتابعين لصفحتنا على الفيس بوك،
and soon we had a quarter of a million followers.
وقريبا سيصبح لدينا ربع مليون متابع.
Our posts and our videos
ملصقاتنا وفيديوهاتنا
were being seen by more than 11 million timelines a week.
شوهدت أكثر من 11 مليون مرة في أسبوع.
It was way more than any newspaper or any magazine could ever do.
تلك طريقة أكثر من أن تقدر أي صحيفة أو مجلة على فعلها أبدًا.
And that turned Mídia NINJA into something else,
وذلك حول ميديا نينجا لشيء آخر،
more than a media outlet, than a media project.
أكثر من منفذ إعلامي، أكثر من مشروع إعلامي.
It became almost like a public service
أصبح تقريبًا مثل خدمة عامة
to the citizen, to the protester,
للمواطن، للاحتجاجات،
to the activist,
للناشط،
because they had a very simple and efficient and peaceful tool
لأنهم لديهم أداة بسيطة جدًا وفعالة وسلمية أيضاً
to confront both police and media authority.
لمواجهة كل من الشرطة وسلطة الإعلام.
Many of our images started to be used in regular TV channels.
العديد من صورنا بدأ التلفزيون النظامي استخدامها.
Our livestreams started to be broadcast even in regular televisions
بثنا المباشر بدأ يذاع حتى عبر التلفزيون النظامي
when things got really rough.
حين أصبحت الأمور حادة.
Some our images were responsible to take some people out of jail,
بعض صورنا كانت جديرة بالثقة لتخرج بعض الناس من السجن،
people who were being arrested unfairly
الناس الذين اعتقلوا بغير حق
under false accusations, and we could prove them innocent.
باتهامات واهية، قدمنا لهم البراءة.
And that also turned Mídia NINJA very soon
وذلك أيضًا حول ميديا نينجا قريبًا جدًا
to be seen as almost an enemy of cops, unfortunately,
لتبدو تقريبًا كعدو لرجال الشرطة، ولسوء الحظ،
and we started to be severely beaten, and eventually arrested on the streets.
بدأنا نُضرب بشدة ونُعتقل مؤخرًا في الشوارع.
It happened in many cases.
حدث هذا في حالات عديدة.
But that was also useful, because we were still at the web,
لكن كان ذلك أيضا مفيد، لأننا كنا لازلنا على شبكة الإنترنت،
so that helped to trigger an important debate in the country
لذا ساعد ذلك على إثارة مناقشات هامة في البلد
on the role of the media itself
عن دور الإعلام نفسه
and the state of the freedom of the press in the country.
وحالة حرية الصحافة في البلد.
So Mídia NINJA now evolved
إذًا تطورت الآن ميديا نينجا
and finally consolidated itself in what we hoped it would become:
ومؤخرًا دمجت نفسها في ما نأمل أن يصبح:
a national network of hundreds of young people,
شبكة قومية من مئات الشباب،
self-organizing themselves locally
ينظمون أنفسهم ذاتيًا بصورة محلية
to cover social, human rights issues,
لتغطية قضايا اجتماعية، وقضايا حقوق الإنسان،
and expressing themselves not only politically
ويعبرون عن أنفسهم ليس فقط سياسيًا
but journalistically.
لكن صحفيًا.
What I started to do in the beginning of this year,
ما بدأت فعله في بداية هذا العام،
as Mídia NINJA is already a self-organizing network,
حيث أصبحت ميديا نينجا شبكة منظمة ذاتيًا بالفعل،
I'm dedicating myself to another project.
أكرس نفسي لمشروع آخر.
It's called Fluxo, which is Portuguese for "stream."
يدعى فلوكسو، اللفظ البرتغالي لــ "تيار"
It's a journalism studio in São Paulo downtown,
إنه ستوديو صحافة في وسط مدينة ساو باولو،
where I used livestream to experiment
حيث استخدم بث مباشر لتجربة
with what I call post-television formats.
ما أدعوه صيغ بعد التليفزيون.
But I'm also trying to come up with ways to finance independent journalism
لكني أحاول أيضًا التوصل إلى طرق لتمويل الصحافة المستقلة
through a direct relationship with an audience,
عبر علاقة مباشرة مع المشاهد،
with an active audience,
مع المشاهد النشط،
because now I really want to try to make a living
لأني الآن حقيقةً أحاول أن أصنع لقمة عيش
out of my tear gas resolution back then.
من قرار الغاز المسيل للدموع آنذاك.
But there's something more significant here,
لكن هناك شيء أكثر خطورة هنا،
something that I believe is more important and more crucial than my personal example.
شيء أعتقد أنه أكثر أهمية وأكثر مصيرية من مثالي الشخصي.
I said that livestream could turn the web into a colossal TV network,
قلت أن البث المباشر يمكنه تحويل الإنترنت لشبكة تليفزيون هائلة،
but I believe it does something else,
لكني أعتقد أنه يفعل شيء آخر،
because after watching people using it,
لأن بعد مشاهدة الناس يستخدمونه،
not only to cover things but to express, to organize themselves politically,
ليس فقط لتغطية مواضيع لكن للتعبير، ولتنظيم أنفسهم سياسيًا،
I believe livestream can turn cyberspace into a global political arena
أنا أؤمن أن البث المباشر يستطيع تحويل الفضاء الإلكتروني لساحة سياسية عالمية
where everyone might have a voice,
حيث كل شخص لديه صوت،
a proper voice,
صوت مناسب،
because livestream takes the monopoly of the broadcast political discourse,
لأن البث المباشر يأخذ احتكار إذاعة الخطاب السياسي،
of the verbal aspect of the political dialogue
من الجانب اللفظي للحوار السياسي
out of the mouths of just politicians and political pundits alone,
من أفواه فقط السياسيون والخبراء السياسيين وحدهم،
and it empowers the citizen through this direct and non-mediated power
وتمنح السلطة للمواطن عبر هذه القوة المباشرة بغير وساطة
of exchanging experiences and dialogue,
من تبادل الخبرات والحوار،
empowers them to question and to influence authorities
تمنحهم القوة لسؤال والتأثير على السلطات
in ways in which we are about to see.
بطرق على وشك أن نراها.
And I believe it does something else that might be even more important,
أنا أؤمن أنها تفعل شيء آخر يمكن حتى أن يكون أكثر أهمية،
that the simplicity of the technology can merge objectivity and subjectivity
بساطة التكنولوجيا يمكن أن تدمج الموضوعية والذاتية
in a very political way, as I see it,
بطريقة سياسية جدًا، كما أراها،
because it really helps the audience,
لأنها حقًا تساعد الجمهور،
the citizen, to see the world through somebody else's eye,
المواطن، على رؤية العالم من خلال عين شخص آخر،
so it helps the citizen to put him- or herself
إذًا تساعد المواطن ليضع نفسه أو نفسها
in other people's place.
في مكان أناس آخرين.
And that idea, I think, should be the intention,
وتلك الفكرة، أعتقد، يجب أن تكون الغاية،
should be the goal of any good journalism, any good activism,
يجب أن تكون الهدف لأي صحافة جيدة، وأي نشاط سياسي جيد،
but most of all, any good politics.
لكن الأهم من ذلك كله، أي سياسة جيدة.
Thank you very much. It was an honor.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم، كان شرف لي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)